你好黑客
hello hackers
我们来谈谈Linux内核中的保护机制
let's talk about mitigations in the Linux kernel
当然，你已经在行动了
of course you have already hit the ground running
你已经在利用内核了
you are exploiting the kernel
但你会遇到这样的情况
but you're running into situations where
该死，shellcode执行不了之类的
shit you can't execute shellcode or etc etc etc
为什么
why
因为保护机制
because mitigations
我们为什么需要保护机制
why do we need them
内核是一个非常受欢迎且价值很高的目标
well the kernel is a very popular and very high value target
内核漏洞十分重要
kernel exploits are truly important
因为它们在某些时候依旧可用
because they are usable in situations
那时候，你可能只有有限的控制权
where you might otherwise have limited control
举个例子
so for example
内核漏洞通常作为漏洞利用链的一部分出现
kernel exploits are very typically present as part of a typical exploit chain
例如，要获取手机的控制权
to take over a mobile phone for example
以一种更通用的方式
and in a kind of more pedestrian way
这种方式存在于许多通用的计算设备中
they're present in a lot of general purpose computing device
利用漏洞来提升特权，还有所有你一直在做的事
exploits to elevate privileges and all the stuff that you've been doing so far
所以这是一个很受欢迎的目标
so it's a popular target
而且它经常受到攻击
and it gets attacked often
在Linux内核和其他内核中发现了许多bug
a lot of bugs get found in the Linux kernel and other kernels
由于各种原因，甚至没全记录在CVE
they don't all even get tracked at CVEs for various reasons
公开、不公开的，都有
from shady to non shady
光CVE记录的，仅在2021年
but even just as track by CVEs in 2021 alone
Linux内核就有149个漏洞
there have been 149 vulnerabilities in the Linux kernel
所以当然内核会受到攻击
so of course the kernel will get attacked
那么我们该怎么做呢
so what do we do about that
显然
obviously
理想情况下，我们能有一个无懈可击的内核
ideally we could have a non attackable kernel
但事实并非如此
but that's not the case
我们还没到那一步
we're not there yet
很久都到不了
we're not going to be there for a very long time
所以我们的选择是
so what we do do is
保护机制
mitigations
与你探索过的用户空间类似
similar to the user space case where you have now explored
有很多很多不同风格的保护机制
tons and tons and tons and tons of different styles and mitigations
内核世界中也有同样的东西
we have the same thing in the kernel world
差不多是这样，内核开发人员说，好吧
basically kernel developers say okay
我们不可能杜绝所有的漏洞
we're not going to be able to prevent all the vulnerabilities
这是不可能的
it's just not possible
所以我们要让攻击者难以下手
so let's make it hard for attackers
难以获取控制权
to actually achieve control
即使他们发现了一个bug，也难以造成重大损害
to actually do significant damage even if they find a bug
大多数保护机制都很熟悉
and most of these mitigations look very familiar
内核有栈金丝雀
the kernel has stack canaries
内核有ASLR
the kernel has ASLR
启动时，会把内核放在一个随机的位置
where at boot it will place the kernel at a random location
内核有NX
the kernel has NX
与在用户空间遇到这些保护机制的体验类似
in a similar way to your user space experience of running into these mitigations as well
如果你对内核的安全态势哲学感兴趣的话
if you're interested in kind of the kernel's security posture philosophy
看看这个链接
take a look at this link
它是一个有趣的阅读材料
it's an interesting read
实际上
and actually
若对内核安全感兴趣，内核文档是个很好的选择
the kernel documentation in general is pretty good if you're interested in kernel security
总之
but the TLDR is that
内核有很多不同的保护机制
the kernel has a lot of various mitigations
当然
but of course
在本课程中，你已经花了很多时间来绕过保护机制
you have spent much of this class bypassing mitigations
你绕过过
so you've bypassed
栈金丝雀，通过泄露它，或跳过它
stack canaries by leaking them or jumping over them
或做一些其他奇特的事情
or doing a number of other exotic things
你在用户空间，绕过过ASLR
you've bypassed ASLR in user space
通过泄漏库基地址
by leaking library based addresses
程序基地址等等
program based addresses etc etc etc
你泄露一个指针
you leak a pointer
就绕过了ASLR
you bypass ASLR
在内核中也是一样的
and it's the same in the kernel
你泄漏一个内核指针
you leak a kernel pointer
就能找出内核的基址
you can figure out where the kernel is based
基于此
and from there
你可以算出来
you can figure out
你想调用的函数在哪里
where whatever functions you want to call
你想要调用的gadget在哪里
whatever gadgets you want to call exist
当然，说到gadget
speaking of gadgets of course
在内核中执行shellcode总会遇到麻烦
you have trouble executing shellcode in the kernel most of the time
因为大多数数据区在内核中是不可执行的
because most data regions are non executed in the kernel
当然你知道如何绕过它
but of course you'll also know how to bypass that
例如用ROP
for example with return oriented programming
所以
so
内核里这个猫鼠游戏一直在进行
the kernel of course has this cat and mouse game etc etc
一个疯狂的解决方案即将到来
one crazy solution that's upcoming
目前还没有得到广泛应用
not really widely deployed right now
是基于函数颗粒度的KASLR
is this concept of function granular KASLR
思路是，不光是加载内核到一个特定的地址了
the idea is aside from just loading the kernel at a specific address
会把内核中所有函数洗个牌
you also have all of the functions in the kernel shuffled around
这是一个有趣的即将到来的保护机制
it's an interesting upcoming mitigation
这将防止你通过泄露地址来绕过KASLR
that will prevent you bypassing KASLR just by leaking an address
但你还是能从泄露的地址中发现很多东西
but there's still a lot of things you find out from leaking an address
在实践中，函数粒度KASLR并不是完整的解决方案
in practice function granular KASLR is not the full solution
你可以在这篇文章中阅读更多关于这个概念的内容
you can read more about the concept in this article that's linked here of the
如果我没记错的话
if I remember correctly
我在这里链接了建议的补丁
i linked here the proposed patch for example
但这是一个部分解决方案
but it's kind of a this partial solution
会有FGKASLR的绕过方法出现
there will be FGKASLR bypasses
这只是战争中防守方的一轮齐射
it's just another volley in this war
还有一些内核专属的保护机制
there is also some very very kernel specific mitigation
因为内核具有非常特殊的安全态势
because the kernel has a very special security posture
因为它在所有用户空间下面
because it lives kind of under all the user land and so forth
坐落在0环
nestled in ring 0
许多漏洞利用攻击内核的方式
the way that many exploits work when they're attacking the kernel
是骗内核，去访问或执行，用户空间的内存数据
is they trick the kernel into accessing or executing memory that's actually in user space
对此有两种保护机制
and there are two mitigations that were created to prevent this from happening
其中一个被称为SMEP
one of them is called SMEP
管理模式执行保护（Intel文档上M是Mode）
Supervisor Memory Execution Protection
它可以防止内核代码跳转到用户空间代码
it prevents kernel code from jumping to user space code
你在内核漏洞利用时
as you've been exploiting the kernel
你可能会想，如果我在这里溢出，修改返回地址
you might think oh if I overflowed the return address here
就能返回到用户空间的shellcode中
I can just have it return into my shellcode in my user space application
现在这样不行了
that is no longer the case
以前，很长一段时间，可以这样
it used to be the case for a long time
但是SMEP出来了
but SMEP came out
在过去的
in the last
我应该查一下
I should have looked this up
SMEP是什么时候出来
when SMEP came out
假设过去5年里，直接跳到用户空间很流行
but let's say in the last 5 years it got very popular
也许是8年
maybe 8 years
SMEP出来了
SMEP came out
它防止了内核代码跳转到用户空间
and it prevents kernel code from jumping to user space
前提，它不是通过syscall对应的sysret等正常途径
without going through the correct return from a syscall etc
这关闭了一个Linux内核的攻击向量
so that closed one exploitation vector let's say of the Linux kernel
还有第二个问题
then there's a second problem of
骗内核，不正确地访问用户空间内存
exploits fooling the kernel into accessing user space memory improperly
有人提出了另一种技术来保护它
and another technique was proposed to protect that
管理模式访问保护（Intel上M是Mode）
Supervisor Memory Access Prevention
总之，SMAP防止内核空间访问用户空间中的内存
anyways SMAP prevents kernel space from accessing memory that's in user space
除非在rflags寄存器中设置了某个标志
unless a flag in the rflags register is set
当然，你可以设置rflags寄存器
now of course you can set the rflags register
在漏洞利用程序中使用stac命令
using the STAC command in your exploit
但这时你已经有代码执行了
but at that point you already have execution
大概率不需要访问用户空间内存
you probably don't need to access user space memory
但它能预防的是
but what it does prevent is
假设
let's say
处理ioctl传过来的对象时，不注意
an uncareful handling of a structure that's passed through an ioctl
它包含了用户空间的指针
containing a user space pointer
导致直接从内核进入用户空间
causing the kernel to go directly into that into user space
为什么要用SMAP和SMEP去分开它
now why is SMEP and SMAP separated it
为什么不直接，
why can't I just say you know what screw it
直接
you just
当你在内核时，用户空间直接当作不存在
user space doesn't exist when you're in the kernel
这是不现实的
well that's not realistic
你需要系统调用传入的参数
you need to be able to pass in arguments through system calls
例如要open的路径参数
for example the path arguments to open
或其他系统调用的各种小结构体参数
or the various you know small structs to other system calls
所以内核需要能够访问用户空间中的内存
and so the kernel needs to be able to access memory in user space
但它是通过使用特定的api来实现的
but it does that by using specific APIs to do that
例如copy_from_user和copy_to_user
such as copy_from_user and copy_to_user
它们会设置正确的标志
which sets the right flag
rflags寄存器中的AC标志
the AC flag in the rflags register
访问内存
does the access
然后清除AC标志
and then clears it again
简单高效
simple mitigation big big Protection
现在
now
在该模块的所有题目中
in all of the challenges in these modules
SMEP和SMAP都打开了
SMEP and SMAP are both on
为什么
why
因为现在是2021年
because it's 2021
我们不会浪费你的智商
we're not going to insult your intelligence
让你去利用现实中没有的漏洞
by having you exploit things that do not exist as problems in real modern deployments anymore
当然，有老的系统没有这些保护机制
of course there're legacy systems that don't have these protections
但在这个模块中
but in this module
我们假设至少这些保护是存在的
we're assuming that at least these protections exist
在这个模块中，KASLR时有时无
KASLR kind of hit and miss in this module
有的题开了
some of our challenges have it on
有的题关了
some of them have it off
但SMEP和SMAP都开了
but SMEP and SMAP are all on
当然
but of course
所有这些保护机制
all of these mitigations
内核漏洞利用，和所有漏洞利用一样，是一门武术
kernel exploitation like all exploitation is a martial art
是攻击者和防御者之间的一场战斗
it's a slow battle between attackers and defenders
有格挡，有击打
there's blocking there's striking
这一切都非常令人兴奋
it's all very exciting
有新技术一直出现
and new techniques are developed all the time
无论是在进攻端还是防守端
both on the offensive and the defensive side
进攻方，针对SMEP的一个回应是
on the offensive side one response to SMEP
例如，在Linux内核中使用run_cmd函数
for example is the use of the run_cmd function in the Linux kernel
Linux内核中的run_cmd只接受一个字符串参数
run_cmd in the Linux kernel just takes a string
用空格分隔
splits it by spaces
它以root身份在用户空间执行给定程序
and runs it as root in user space
显然这是一个非常强大的手段
obviously that's a very powerful primitive
它是一个内核函数
it's a kernel function
如果你有内核中的代码执行
so if you have kernel code execution
并且你能用可控参数调用一个函数
and you can call a function with a controlled argument
那run_cmd就是你的朋友
boom run_cmd is your friend
你不必主动返回到用户空间
you don't have to return to userspace
你不需要做很多事情
you don't have to do a lot of things
你可以直接以root身份运行命令
you can just run a command as root
如果你对它的工作原理感兴趣的话
if you're interested in how that actually works under the hood
你可以在Bootlin上阅读源代码
you can look up the source code on Bootlin
它是了解内核概念的极好的资源
it's an awesome resource for looking up kernel concepts
这是最新版本源码的链接
that's a link to the latest version
我记得pwncollege现在用的版本是5.4
I think the version that we're running in pwn College right now is 5.4
但这是非常相似的
but it's very analogous
感兴趣的话，你可以在bootlin上查找对应的版本
and you can actually change Bootlin to look at the correct version that you're interested in
这只是一种绕过方法
so this is just one kind of bypass
这是一个很简单的绕过方法
I mean it's very cheap as a bypass
它就是运行命令
it just you know runs commands
但它是可行的
but it's quite viable
所有要先跳回用户空间，再做复杂的ROP的利用手段
so all of these exploits that used to have to jump back into user space code or do complex ROP
大概率都可直接调用run_cmd
could just potentially call run_cmd
显然还有其他的
obviously there are other
高级的内核漏洞利用技术
advanced kernel exploitation techniques
但在大多数情况下
but for the most part
对于这个模块，你只要了解掌握基础知识
for this module you are really mastering the basics
能在内核中成功地进行操作。就行
to be able to operate in the kernel successfully